okay here's linear
algebra lecture
s I've been talking
about Vector spaces and especially the
null space of a matrix and the column
space of a matrix what's in those spaces
now I want to actually
describe them H how do you describe all
the vectors that are in those spaces how
do you compute these things so this is
the uh turning the idea the definition
into an algorithm what's the algorithm
for solving ax equals z so that's the
null space that I'm interested in so can
I take a particular Matrix a and
describe the natural algorithm and I'll
execute it for that
Matrix uh here we go uh so let me take
the Matrix as an example so we're
definitely talking rectangular matrices
in this chapter so I'll make I'll have
four
columns and three rows 2
468 and 36810
okay if I just look at those columns uh
and
rows well I noticed right away that
column two is a multiple of column one
it's in the same direction as column one
it's not
independent I I'll expect to discover
that in the process actually with rows I
noticed that that row plus this row
gives the third
row so the third row is not
independent so uh all that should come
out of elimination so now what am I my
my algorithm is
elimination but extended now to the
rectangular case where we have to
continue even
if there's zeros in the pivot position
we go on okay so let me execute
elimination for that
Matrix my goal is oh was while I'm doing
elimination I'm not changing the null
space that's very important right I'm
solving ax equals z by elimination and
when I do these operations that you
already know when I subtract a multiple
of one equation from another
equation I'm not changing in the
solutions so I'm not changing the null
space actually I am changing the column
space as you'll see so you have to pay
attention what does elimination leave
unchanged and it the answer is the
solutions to the system are not changed
because I'm doing the same thing to I'm
doing a legitimate operations on the
equations of course on the right hand
side it's always zero and I don't plan
to write zero all the time
okay so I'm really just working on the
left side but the right side
is is keeping up always zeros okay so
what's
elimination well you know where the
first pivot is and you know what to do
with it so can I just take the first
step below here so that pivot row is
fine I take two times that row away from
this one and I get zero
Z that's signaling a difficulty two two
tws away from the six leaves me with a
two two tws away from the eight leaves
me with a four and now three of those
away from here is zero again another
zero 3 tws away from that eight is the
two 3 twos away from that 10 is a four
okay that's the first stage of
elimination I've got the First Column
straight
so of course I move on to the second
column I look in that position I see a
zero I look below it hoping for a
nonzero that I can do a row exchange but
it's zero
below so that's telling me that that
column is well what it's really going to
be telling me is that that column is a
combination of the earlier column it's
depend that second column is dependent
on the earlier column but I don't stop
to think
here that column there's nothing to do I
go on to the next so here's the next
pivot so there's the first pivot and
there's the second pivot can I just keep
this elimination going downwards so so
the next step keeps the first row
keeps the second
row with its pivot so I've got my two
pivots and does
elimination to clear out the column
below that pivot so actually you see the
multiplier is one it subtracts row two
from Row three and produces a row of
zeros okay that I would I would call
that Matrix U right that's our
upper well I can't quite say upper
triangular uh maybe upper I don't know
upper something it's got
uh it's it's in this so-called Echelon
form e the word Echelon means like
staircase form it's the the nonzeros
come in that staircase form if there was
another pivot
here the then the staircase would
include that but here's a case where we
have two pivots only okay so actually
we've already discovered the most
important number about this
Matrix the number of
pivots is
two that number we will call the rank of
the Matrix so let me put it put
immediately the
rank of
a so I'm telling you what the this word
rank
means in the algorithm it's equal to the
number of
pivots and in this case
two okay for me that number two is the
crucial number okay now I go to you
remember I'm always solving ax equals z
but now I can solve uux equals 0 right
same Solutions same null space okay so I
could stop here why don't I why don't I
stop here and do the back substitution
so now I have to ask you how do I
describe the
solutions there are solutions right to
ax equals z I knew there would be I had
three equations in four unknowns I
certainly expected some solutions now I
want to see what are they okay here's
the critical
step I and I refer to it up here as
separating out the pivot variables the
pivot columns which are these two here I
have two pivot columns those are those
obviously they're The Columns with the
pivot so I have two
pivot
columns and I have the other
columns I'll call free two these are
free columns
okay why do I use those words why do I
use that word
free because now I want to write I want
to find the solutions to ux equals z
here's the way I do
it these free
columns I can assign any number freely
to those to those to those to the to the
variables X2 and
X4 the ones that multiply columns 2 and
four so I can assign anything I like to
X2 and
X4 and
then I can solve the equations for X1
and X3 let me say that again if I give
let me let me assign so so one
particular
X is to assign say the value one to the
to X2 and zero to
X4 those are that was a free choice but
it's a convenient Choice okay now I want
to solve ux equals 0 and find numbers 1
and three F complete the solution okay
can I write down let's see shall we just
remember what ux equals 0 represents
what are my equations that first
equation is X1 plus just
I'm just saying what are these matrices
of meaning that's the first equation and
the second equation was
2x3 +
4x4 = 0 those are my two
equations okay now the point is I can
find X1 and
X3 by back substitution so we're
building on what we already know the new
thing is that there were some some free
variables that I could give any numbers
to and I'm systematically going to make
a choice like this one and zero now what
is
X3 let's let's go backwards back up I
look at the last
equation X3 is zero from the last
equation because because
X4 we've we've set X4 to zero and then
we get X3 as zero okay now we set X2 to
be one so what is
X1 -2 right so that I have -2 + 2 0 and
0 correctly giving zero there is a
vector in the null
space there's a solution to ax equals 0
in fact what solution is that that
simply says that -2 * the First Column
plus 1 * the second column is the zero
column of course that's right minus two
of that column plus one of that or minus
two of that plus one of that that
solution is that that's just what we saw
immediately that the second column is
twice as big as the First Column okay
tell me some more vectors in the null
space I found
one tell me uh how to get a bunch more
immediately out of that one just take
multiples of it it any multiple of I
could multiply this by anything I might
as well call it I could say C some
multiple of this so let
me so X could be any multiple of this
one okay that that describes now a line
an infinitely long line in
four-dimensional
space
but which is in the null space is that
the whole null space
no I've got two free variables here I
made this Choice One and zero for the
free variables but I could have made
another Choice let me make the other
choice zero and
one you see my
system it my so let me repeat the system
this is the algorithm that you you
just learn to
do find do do elimination
decide which are the pivot columns and
which are the free columns that tells
you that that variables 1 and three are
pivot variables two and four are free
variables then those free variables you
assign them you you give one of them the
value one and the others the value zero
in this case we had a one and a zero and
complete the solution and you do you
give the other one the value one and and
zero and now complete to solution so
let's complete that solution I'm looking
for a vector in the null space and it's
absolutely going to be different from
this guy because uh because any multiple
of that zero is never going to give the
one so I have somebody new in the null
space and let me finish it out what's X3
here so we're going by back substitution
looking at this equation now X4 we've
changed we're doing the other
possibility where X2 is zero and X4 is 1
so X3 will happen to be
min-2 and now what do I get for that
first
equation uh X1 let's see 2 x3s is min -4
plus two do I get a two
there perhaps yeah two for
X1 - 4 and two okay that's in the null
space what does that say
about the columns that says that two of
this
column minus two of this column plus
this column gives zero which it
does two of that minus two of that and
one of that gives the zero column okay
now now I found another Vector in the
null space now we're ready to tell me
the whole null space what are all the
solutions to ax equals 0
I've got this guy and when I have him
what else is goes into the null space
along with
that these are my two special
Solutions I call them special I just
invented that name special Solutions
what's special about them is the special
numbers I gave to the free
variables the values zero and one for
the free variables I could have given
the free variables any values and got
vectors in the null space but this was a
good way to be sure I got got everybody
okay so once I have him I also have any
multiple right so I could take any
multiple of that and it's in the null
space and now what else I left a little
space for what
what a plus sign I can take any
combination here's a line of vectors in
the null space a bunch of solutions
would you rather I say in the null space
or would you rather I say okay I'm
solving ax equals z well really I'm
solving ux equals
z well okay let me put in that crucial
plus sign I'm taking all the
combinations of my two special Solutions
that that's my conclusion
now the null space contains contains
exactly all the combinations of the
special
Solutions and how many special Solutions
are there there's one for every free
variable and how many free variables are
there oh I mean we can see all the whole
picture now if if the rank R was two
this is the this is the number of pivot
variables right because it counted the
pivots so how many free
variables well you know it's two
right what is it in for a matrix that's
M rows n columns n variables that means
with rank
R how many free variables have we got
left if R of the variables are pivot
variables we have n minus r in this case
4-2 fre
variables you see that first of
all we get a ni we get clean answers
here we get R pivot variables so there
really were our equation equations here
there looked like three equations but
there were really only two independent
equations and there were n minus
r variables that we could choose freely
and we gave them those special 01 uh
values and we got the special
Solutions
okay that for me we could stop at that
point that gives you a complete
algorithm
for finding all the solutions to ax
equals
z
okay again you do
elimination going onward when a
column when when there's nothing to be
done on one column you just
continue that this number R the number
of pivots is
crucial and it leaves n minus r free
variables which you give value Zer and
one to I would like to take one more
step I would like to clean up this
Matrix even more so now I'm going to go
to this is in its this is in Echelon
form upper triangular if you like I want
to go one more step to make it as good
as it can be okay so now I'm going to
speak about the reduced
row Echelon form okay so now I'm going
to speak about the Matrix R which is the
reduced row
Echelon
form so what does that mean that means I
just I I can I can work harder on you so
let me start let me suppose I got as far
as
U which was good
notice how that row of zeros appeared I
I didn't comment on that but I I should
have that row of zeros appeared because
Row three was a combination of rows one
and two and elimination discovered that
fact when we get a row of zero that's
telling us that the that that the
original row that was
there was a combination of other rows
and elimination knocked it
out okay so we got this far now how can
I clean that up further I can do uh
elimination
upwards I can get zero above the pivots
so this reduced row Echelon form has
zeros
above and
below the
pivots so let me do
that so now I'll subtract one of this
from the row above that will leave a
zero and a minus two in there
and that's
good okay and I can clean it up even one
more step I can make the
pivots the pivots I'm going to make
equal to one because I can divide
equation two by the
pivot that won't change the solutions so
let me do that and then I really I'm
ready to stop 1 2 0- 2 0 0 1 two I
divided the second equation by two
because now I have a one in the
pivot and Zer below okay this is my
Matrix
R I guess I'm hoping that you could now
execute the whole
algorithm mat lab will do it immediately
with the
command RR R
EF Ro reduced row Echelon form of a so
if I input that original Matrix a and
then I write then I type that
command press return that Matrix will
appear That's the reduced row Echelon
form
and it's got all the
information as
clear as can be
what what information has it got well of
course it immediately tells me the pivot
rows pivot rows one and two pivot
columns one and
three and in fact it's got the identity
Matrix in there right it's it's got
zeros above and below the pivots and the
pivots are one so it's so it's got a so
notice the 2x two identity Matrix
that's sitting in the pivot rows and
pivot columns it's it's it's I in the
pivot
rows and
columns it's got zero rows
below those are always indicating that
original rows were were combinations of
other rows so we really only had two
rows there and now it also so there's
the identity now it's also got its
free
columns and uh they're cleaned up as
much as possible actually actually it's
now so cleaned up that the special
Solutions I can read off you you
remember I went through the steps of
computing this uh
this uh doing back
substitution let me let me instead of
that system let me take this improved
system so I'm going to use these
numbers right in these equations what
did I do I divided this equation by
two and oh yeah and I had subtracted two
of this which knocked out this guy and
made that a minus sign is that what
that's that's now I've now written RX
equals
0 now I guess I'm hoping everybody in
this room understands the the solutions
to the original ax equals z the Midway
halfway ux equal Z and the final RX
equals 0 all the
same because going from one of those to
another one I didn't mess up I I just
multiplied equations and subtracted from
other equations which I'm allowed to
do okay but my point is that
now if I do this free variables and back
substitution it's just the numbers are
there when I let X so in this guy I let
X2 be one
and X4
b0 I I guess what am I seeing here let
me let me sort of separate this out here
I'm seeing in the
pivot in the pivot columns if I if I put
the pivot columns here I'm seeing those
and I'm in the free
columns I'm seeing what am I seeing in
the free columns the two Z and that
first free column the the X2 column and
a minus 22 in the in the in the fourth
column the other free column and and the
row of zeros
below which of course have
no that equation is 0 equals z that's
satisfying here's my
point that when I do back
substitution these numbers are exactly
what shows
up oh their signs get switched I was
going to say those numbers 2 - 2
02 can I just circle the this is the
free part of the Matrix this is the
identity
part this is the free part maybe I'll
call it
F this of course I call I because it's
the
identity the free part is a I mean I'm
just doing back
substitution and the those free numbers
will show up with a minus sign because
they pop onto the other side of the
equation so I see min-2 0 and I see 2
-2 C can I so that wasn't magic it had
to
happen let me uh show you clearly why it
happened okay so that's this this is
what I'm interested in here and now let
me let me just like do it do it for or
let's suppose
we've we've got
to let's suppose we've got this system
already
in in our
RF
form so my Matrix R is what does it look
like can
I'll let me pretend that the pivot
columns come first and then whatever is
in the free cup and there might be some
zero rows
below there's a
typical a pretty
typical reduced row Echelon
form you see what's typical it's it's
got this is R by R this is this this is
R pivot rows
this is our pivot
columns and here are n minus r free
columns okay tell me what are the
special
Solutions what are the what's what's X
if I want to solve RX equals z in fact
let
me I'm really going to uh do the whole
since these this is now block matrices I
might as well do all of the special
Solutions at once so I want to solve RX
equal
0 and I'll have some special
Solutions let me
actually can I do them all at once I'm
going to create a null space Matrix
okay
matrix it's it's it's
columns are the special solute The
Columns are the special
Solutions this is I'm making it sound
harder it's going to be totally easy n
will be this null space Matrix I want
r n to be the zero Matrix these Columns
of n are supposed to multi get
multiplied by R and give zero
columns so what n will do the job let me
put I'm going to put the identity in the
free variable part and then minus F will
show up in
the pivot variables just the way it did
in that example there we had the
identity and F here and in the special
solution so these columns are there's
the Matrix of special Solutions and
actually there so there's a matlb
command or a teaching code
command
null n equal so this is the the produces
the null basis the null space Matrix
null of a and there it is do you
so and how does that command actually
work it uses matlb to compute
R then it picks out the pivot variables
the free variables puts puts ones and
zeros in for the free variables and
copies out the pivot variables it it
does back substitution but back
substitution for this system is totally
simple what what is this
system uh RX =
Z so this is R is i
f and X is the pivot
variables and the free
variables and it's supposed to give
zero so what does that mean that means
that the pivot
variables plus f * the free variables
give zero
so let me put ftimes the free variables
on the other side I get minus
ftimes the free
variables there's there's my uh equation
as simple as it can
be that's that's what back substitution
comes to when I've reduced and reduced
and reduced this system to the to the
best form okay and
uh then if the free variables I make
this special choice of the identity then
the pivot V pivot variables are minus F
okay can I do uh another example could
you do another example can I let me just
take another Matrix and and let's go
through this algorithm once more
okay here we go here's a Blackboard for
another
Matrix
okay so I'll call The Matrix a again but
let me make it uh yeah how big should we
make it this
time ah why don't I do this just for the
heck of it let me take the transpose of
this
a and see what happens to
that 2
468 and 3 6 8 10
before we do the calculations tell me
what's
coming how many pivot variables do you
expect
here how many columns are going to have
pivots how
[Music]
many we have three columns in that
Matrix but are we going to are we going
to have three
pivots no because
this third column is the sum of the
first two columns I'm totally expecting
totally expecting that these will be
pivot
columns because they're
independent but that this third guy the
third column which is dependent on the
first two is going to be a free column
elimination better discover that and
elimination will also straighten out the
rows we'll also Identify some zero some
some dependent rows and some independent
rows what's the what's the row reduced
Echelon form for this let's just do it
okay so so that's the first pivot two *
that away from that gives me a row of
zeros two * that away from that gives me
a
022 and 2 * that away from that gives me
a 0
okay First Column is straight first
variable is a pivot variable no problem
on to the second column I look at the
second pivot it's a
zero I look below it there's a two okay
I do a row
exchange so this zero is now there I now
have a perfectly good
pivot and I use it
okay and I subtract two of that row away
from this row you all right if I do it
like that I I've got to the form U now
this was my a now there's my
U I can see I can see now I I have to
stop right I would go on to the third
column I should have
tried I quit but without trying I
shouldn't have done that on to the third
column look at the pivot position it's
got a zero in it look below all zeros
now I'm entitled to stop okay so the
rank is two
again uh what about the null space how
many special Solutions are there this
time how many special solutions for this
Matrix I've got an which are the free
variables and which are the pivot
variables and so on pivot columns I've
got two pivot
columns and that's no accident the
number of pivot columns for a matrix
a that's a great
fact that the number of pivot columns
for a and a trans a transpose are the
same and then I have a free column
there's a free
column one free column because the count
is 3 -
2 3 - 2 gives me one free
column okay so now let me solve
uh what's in the null space okay so how
do I H let's see these vectors have
length three they only have three
components I'm making too much space for
the to write X
X has just got three components and what
are
they I'm looking for the null
space okay so how do I
start I give the free
variable some convenient value and
what's
that I set it to one I set the free
variable to one if I set the free
variable to zero and solve for the pivot
variables I'll get all zeros no
progress but by setting the free
variable to one you see my two equations
now are shall I my equations are X1 +
2x2 + 3x3 is z that's my first equation
and my second equation is now 2x2 + 2x3
=
0 and uh okay so if X3 is 1 then X2
is
minus1 and if X3 is 1 and X2 is min -1
then maybe X1 is
minus1 and actually I go back to check
now I don't
like I I did I did a quick calculation
mentally can I mentally do a quick check
that Matrix that solution X says that
minus this column minus this column plus
this one is the zero column and it is
minus that minus that plus that is zero
so that's in the null space and now you
can tell me what else is in the null
space what's what's the whole null space
now it's I multiply by C right the whole
null space is a
line so that's the description if I ask
you on a homework or a quiz or the final
what give me describe tell me the null
space find the null space of this
Matrix you could take those
steps and that's the answer I'm looking
for and I'm looking for that c too
because that's telling me that you're
remembering that it's a whole space and
not just one
vector later I will ask you for a basis
for the null space then I just want this
Vector but if I ask for the whole null
space then there's the whole line
through that Vector okay now one more
natural thing to do with this example
right is keep going to
the the reduced Matrix R so can I push
onwards to r that should be quick but
let's just practice let me keep going to
R okay so what do I do here I subtract I
I want I clear out above the pivot so I
subtract that from that that's one1 is
left right when I subtracted this Row
from this it produces zero Above This
pivot and now I want that pivot to be a
one so for the r Matrix I'll divide this
equation by
two and of course these zero zeros are
great they don't change there's R that's
r you see what R is you see the identity
Matrix sitting up
here you see the Free Part F the F part
here and you see the zeros below this is
if F0
0 and what's the
X the X has the
identity well it's only a single number
one but it's the identity Matrix in the
free in the free part and what does it
have in
the pivot variables what did back
substitution give it gave minus these
guys you see that what this is is any
multiple of this is the identity there
and this is minus F
here that's our null space this is our
null space Matrix
n for this our our null space Matrix is
the guy whose columns are the special
Solutions so their free variables have
these special values one and
the pivot variables have minus F so do
you see the how the minus F just
automatically shows up in the special
Solutions that's it really I I don't
think there's anything more I can
say about ax equals z there's more I can
say about ax equal
B but that'll be uh Friday okay so
that's that's the null space thanks